不少人认为火箭的垂直起飞垂直着陆(VTVL)技术
You may well be forgiven for thinking that Rockets which take off vertically
是太空叉和蓝源最近才出现的新技术，这无可厚非
and then land again vertically were a recent development by the likes of Blue Origin and SpaceX
但快速回首火箭发展史
But a quick look back into the history of rocketry
你会发现这项技术一点都不新奇，距离其首次使用已经有六十年之久
and you'll see that this technique is far from new and was first used nearly sixty years ago
让火箭VTVL需要很多技术的整合
Just to get a rocket to take off and land vertically requires a lot of technology to come together
首先你要有足够推力起飞
You need to have enough thrust to take off
还要有留有足够燃料返回地球
but then enough fuel left to descend back to earth
你还需要可重复启动的发动机，返回时还要承受高超音速的再入
you also need to be able to relight the engines and up to hypersonic speeds as the rocket falls back to the ground
你的发动机要能摇摆，从而控制返回时的姿态保证不失控
You need to be able to gimbal or tilt the engines and the Rockets angle of descent without it tumbling out of control
你的发动机还得有节流能力
You also need to be able to throttle down the engines to a small amount of thrust comparable
同一台发动机要节流到只有起飞推力的很小一部分
to that which is required to launch the rocket with the same engines
你还要有着陆腿，还要有伸缩着陆腿的机构
And you need legs to land on, and the mechanism of which to deploy them
像这种用尾翼当着陆腿的火箭
The image of rockets landing vertically on their tail fins
从上世纪三十年代以来人们就已经见得多了
has been popularized in science fiction since the early 1930s
尽管该技术真正实现花了将近三十年
though it took nearly 30 years to bring the technology to a point
这些技术基本上已经成熟，但应用的地方可能和你想的有点偏差
where it could be used practically though it wasn't quite in the way you might have expected
第一个以火箭为动力的VTVL
The first instance of a rocket-powered vertical takeoff and vertical landing
出现在1961年的Bell火箭腰带上
was shown in 1961 with the Bell Rocket Belt
尽管第一个火箭背包早在1919年就由毛子Alexander Andreyev发明并申请专利了
Although the first rocket pack had been developed and patented by a Russian Alexander Andreyev in 1919
之后还有不少人说自己发明出会飞的背包
and various people since have claimed to have invented things like the flying rucksack
但直到五十年代Bell航天系统才让他们的火箭腰带应用到美军
It wasn't until the mid-1950s that Bell AeroSystems starting work on the Bell Rocket Belt for the US Army
它使用过氧化氢发动机
The rocket belt used a hydrogen peroxide engine
但19升的燃料罐只够飞21秒，飞行120米的距离
but the 19 liters of fuel in the tanks could only provide 21 seconds of flight and travelled around about a 120 meters
但当公众看后惊了
But it was a hit with the public
不但来了个“全球巡演”，还出现在1965年詹姆斯·邦德的《007之霹雳弹》中
|and it was toured around the world and also appeared in the 1965 James Bond film Thunderball
但美军哪用得着“只能飞120米”的东西？所以就把合同取消了
But the US army were less impressed with the amount of backup required
to get one man 120 meters and they canceled the contract
但几年后，就出现了一个火箭动力、垂直着陆垂直起飞的载具
But within a few years there would be a rocket-powered vertical takeoff and vertical landing vehicle
全球数亿人都见证了它的成功
that would be a total success and be seen by hundreds of millions of people around the world
那就是阿波罗登月舱
That vehicle was the Apollo Lunar Lander
专门用于人类所去过的最不适宜居住的地方
a design that was used in the most inhospitable place man had ever been to
并且六次着陆无一失败
and worked without fail on six separate missions
虽然这个过程是反过来的(先垂直着陆再垂直起飞, VLVT)，它是先从月球轨道着陆
Though when you think about it it actually worked in reverse because it dropped from orbit to land on the moon
然后作为登月舱的部分——上升段起飞
and then the ascent module which was only part of a lunar lander took off to return the crew
送乘员返回指令舱，最后返回地球
back to the command module and then back onto earth
月球还有一个吼，就是重力只有地球的六分之一
There was also an advantage to landing on the moon because it only has one sixth of gravity of that on the Earth
对抗重力是火箭最大的难题
Fighting gravity is the biggest issue for any rocket
但登月舱下降发动机还要能够悬停并寻找落点
but particularly one which had to slow and hover to find a landing spot
虽然登月舱配有某些雷达可以自动检测离地高度
Although the lander had some automation in the form of radar to detect the distance from the ground
并有电脑控制唯一的一台发动机
and computer control of a single engine
当雷达本该在着陆最后阶段关闭却没关的时候
When the radar which should have been turned off for the final part of a descent was accidentally left on
它的大量数据过载了计算机
it overloaded the computer with data
计算机挂掉后，阿姆斯特朗只能手动控制登月舱着陆
Without the computer it fell to Neil Armstrong to manually land the lander on the surface of the Moon
阿姆斯特朗非常熟悉着陆的那一套理论
Armstrong was well versed with the procedure
他在地球版本的登月舱训练过——它有个亲切的名字叫会飞的床架
as he had trained on the Earth-based version of the lander which was affectionately known as the Flying Bedstead
在地球的重力下，且没有计算机的帮助
In Earth's gravity and with no computers to help him
他说控制那东西就像在扫帚棍上顶盘子一样
he described controlling it as like trying to balance a plate on the end of a broom handle
某次一个推进器没燃料了，他只有一秒的反应时间去弹出
and on one occasion when a thruster ran out of fuel he had just a second notice to eject
从鬼门关里走了一遭，而载具失控坠毁
and avoid almost certain death as the vehicle lost control and crashed
这告诉了我们，着陆这件事情有多难
This shows just how difficult it is to actually land something
尤其是用火箭发动机把一个又高又瘦的东西着陆
which is powered by rockets especially an object which is tall and thin
而且不是像登月舱那样VLVT，而是VTVL
and not really designed to come back in the reverse manner of how it took off
直到九十年代，才出现了真正的先垂直起飞再垂直着陆的火箭
It wasn't until the mid 1990s but the first true vertical takeoff and vertical landing rocket was seen
它就是麦道家的三角快帆-X——DC-X
in the form of the McDonnell Douglas Delta Clipper Experimental for DC-X
这个使用现成零件的更便宜的单级入轨(SSTO)载具的理念
The idea of a low-cost single-stage-to-orbit vehicle using off-the-shelf components
在1985年由麦道的前太空系统工程师Max Hunter提出
was proposed to McDonnell Douglas in 1985 by Max Hunter, their ex-chief engineer for Space Systems
此人从六十年代起就已经在构思这个概念
who had been thinking of the concept since the 60s
但麦道本身对此理念并没有太大兴趣
but Mcdonnell Douglas weren't interested in funding the idea themselves
所以同样还为里根总统的战略防御计划组织工作的Hunter
So Hunter who had also worked for President Ronald Reagan's Strategic Defense Initiative Organization or SDIO
与Jerry Pournelle、Graham将军一起游说副总统Dan Quayle
went with Jerry Pournelle and General Graham to sell the idea to Vice President Dan Quayle
他们假设任何基于太空的防御系统一定需要一个运输系统
on the premise that any space-based defense system would need a delivery system
该系统要非常便宜、可靠，比航天飞机复用速度快
that would be far cheaper, more reliable, and with much faster turnaround times than the space shuttle
项目通过，还扛着SDIO的大旗
With the approval of a project and it coming under the SDIO banner
该项目直接撇开NASA和空军那边不管
away from the bureaucracy of NASA and the Air Force
直接在麦道组了一百来人的团队
it allowed the small team of around a hundred people at McDonnell Douglas
从1991年开始，在21个月里造了一个三分之一缩尺模型原型机，造价仅六千万
to build a one-third scale prototype in just 21 months for a cost of just $60 million dollars starting in 1991
该设计让火箭像往常一样垂直起飞，然后垂直着陆回原来的位置
The design would take off like a normal rocket and then land back again in the same vertical position
不使用降落伞，使用和起飞相同的发动机，着陆在伸出的着陆腿上
as it took off on extendable legs under its own power and without any parachutes
原型机设计上就是无法入轨的，实际上最高也只飞到2.5千米
The prototype was never designed to go into orbit and in fact only of a flew to a height of around 2.5 km
但也够验证这一理念了
but that was enough to prove the concept
外壳使用复合材料按缩尺比定制
The outer shell was custom-built by Scale Composites
剩余部分比如RL-10A发动机、控制系统都是现成的组件
and the rest of a craft including the RL-10A engines and the control systems were off-the-shelf components
测试从1993年开始，其间进行三次试飞
The testing program started in 1993 and flew three test flights
直到战略防卫计划结束，资金耗尽
until funding ran out as a result of the SDI program coming to an end
NASA后来补了点钱，测试继续
NASA provided further funding and testing resumed
一次飞行中，DC-X发生一次小型爆炸，侧面炸出一个可见的洞
On one flight a minor explosion occurred and the DC-X can be seen with a hole in its side
但它成功执行终止程序并自动降落
but it successfully performed an abort and an auto landing
修复后在1995年继续进行测试
After the repairs it continued testing in 1995
但后来一次重着陆，摔裂了外壳，资金又断了
But after a hard landing cracked the outer shell and again funding had been cut
坏的地方没钱修
there was not enough funds to carry out repairs
好说歹说NASA在1995年接手了项目，毕竟它之前飞行还是挺成功的
During 1995 NASA begrudgingly agreed to take on the project because of its previous test flight successes
但经过几次升级后，项目改名DC-XA
But with several upgrades and the project would be renamed as the DC-XA
在1996年测试继续，不过这次它有了一个对手
In 1996 testing resumed but this time it was also in competition
那就是洛克希德马丁的X-33冒险之星项目
with the Lockheed Martin X-33 Venture Star Project
NASA将该项目作为替代航天飞机的选择之一
which NASA had chosen as a possible replacement for the Shuttle
最终DC-X输了，按NASA的解释，原因是“资金短缺”
And ultimately the DC-X lost out to what NASA said were budgetary constraints
但更根本原因是X-33才是亲儿子项目，NASA单纯想钦点DC-X项目下马罢了
but too many the X-33 was NASA's pet project and the DC-X was something they didn't really want
即使造一个新的DC-XA只要五千万
Even though the cost of building a new DC-XA was just $50 million
和别的火箭想比还是挺便宜的
a very cheap price when compared to other rocket projects
NASA之后几年又在X-33项目上花了9.2个亿
NASA would go on to spend $920M on the X-33 over the next few years
最后复合材料油箱整不明白，项目还是取消了
only to cancel it at the last minute due to technical issues with the composite fuel tanks
并且这玩意一次都没飞起来过
and before any test flights had taken place
尽管DC-X挂了，但它鼓励了蓝源的新薛帕德火箭
Although the DC-X was at an end, it inspired the Blue Origin New Shepard
当年参与DC-X项目的一些工程师也被蓝源挖去
and some of the engineers which worked on the DC-X project went on to work at Blue Origin
太空叉就一句话也不说，我们也能在猎鹰九号上看到很多DC-X的影子
Although SpaceX won't say directly we can see the influence of the DC-X on the Falcon 9 reusable rockets too
一些NASA的工程师也相信利用DC-X的理念
Some NASA engineers also believe that DC-X concept
可以制造出最多可载六人的火星着陆器
would make a good Mars Lander with a crew of up to six people
在地球上的测试证明其到了弱重力的火星是可行的
The testing on earth proved that it could be done and with the weaker gravity of Mars
运力可以得到极大提升
the payload capacity would be greatly enhanced
所以我们今天看到太空叉和蓝源都用的和DC-X类似的技术
And so we come to the present day with both SpaceX and Blue Origen, both using similar techniques to the DC-X
虽然DC-X项目的取消留给了他们足够的时间追赶，但设计出人意料的快
Though with the benefit of the extra time since the demise of the DC-X, the designs have moved on considerably
猎鹰九号很快就证明了它可以运送商业载荷和军用载荷入轨
with the SpaceX Falcon 9 proving that it can be used for delivering commercial and military payloads into orbit
甚至还能送一辆车去火星
and even sending a car to Mars
他们说站在巨人的肩膀上就没啥新东西可学了
They say that there is nothing new and that we stand on the shoulders of giants
这话倒也没错
and that's pretty much true
但每一步都需要有才能者了解前人的成果，才能创造新的东西
But each step of a way needs skilled people to fully understand what has gone before in order to build the new ideas
就像DC-X验证了垂直起飞、空中机动和垂直着陆的方法一样
Just as the DC-X proved a principle of vertical takeoff in air maneuvering and vertical landing
太空叉参考了那些方法，还找到了新的实现方法并应用之
SpaceX have taken those principles and found new solutions to enable them
创造了完全可商用的可回收火箭运载系统
to make a fully working reusable rocket delivery system
而这些成就还会鼓励有才能者继续迈出下一步
and that takes people that have the skills to make those next steps
字幕翻译给虫 记得点赞投币分享收藏关注转发
我们视频的赞助商Brilliant.org就是致力于让你获取这些才能的
Our sponsor for this video Brilliant.org is dedicated to helping you gain those skills
让你变成一个真正的会计算的科学家
turning you into a living breathing and most importantly calculating scientist
去那看看吧，看你自己能不能让火箭入轨
Head over there and prove yourself what it takes to get a rocket into orbit
拥有强大的数学和科学技能是很关键的，因为它们才是我们探索宇宙的铺路石
Having a strong math and science skills set is crucial because it opens so many ways to explore the universe
想要支持YouTube频道Curious Droid或者了解更多有关Brilliant网站的内容
To support Curious Droid and learn more about Brilliant
请前往下面这个链接，免费注册
go to brilliant.org/curiousdroid and sign up for free
最先发射入轨的前200人
So if you're ready to launch off the planet and the first 200 people
可以得到年费会员的20%优惠
will get a 20% discount off of the annual premium subscription